today we're going to model the daily
average temperature of sydney
observatory now we're going to be
looking at temperature data over the
last 160 years
we're going to identify a long term
trend and then model seasonal variants
using a fourier series now because our
choice is going to be a first order
fourier series we're actually able to
use non-linear
least-squared regression to be able to
estimate these parameters of the model
so without further ado let's jump into
it so de-trending and modeling seasonal
variation with fourier series so
essentially it's just a time series
decomposition and this is a technique
that actually splits the time series
into several different components each
representing an underlying pattern and
category so here is our time series y
which is actually our temperature our
daily average temperature and then we've
got a trend component and a trend we're
just going to notice is it decreasing is
it constant or is it increasing over
time we have a seasonality component
which is just the periodic signal that
is being observed over a given frequency
and then we have the noise which is the
variability in the data that cannot be
explained by the time series model that
we have so the model that we're actually
going to have is deterministic seasonal
mean temperature of our daily average
temperature
series and we're going to model this
with a trend component and a seasonal
component
so daily average temperature series is
from sydney observatory we have data
going back from uh first of january
1859 to today so just over 160 years
now the temperature series that you can
see here is just plotted um from the
late 90s through to today and what
you'll notice is that we have quite a
lot of variation in noise so the first
thing we're going to do is actually
denoise this daily average temperature
series
one of the ways we can actually do this
is by using a simple algorithm that
signal processing industry have used for
exactly this purpose and that is
convolutions
now convolutions is just a mathematical
operation whereby we are convoluting one
function with another
now
here a convolution is just the area
under the curve of these two functions
that are moved towards each other and
then away from one another aka convolved
so an applied convolution ends up
looking like this here i've just used a
square function and then convolved it
with our time series data and
essentially what we've got is a nice
smooth denoised temperature series so
let's start with the long term trends
if i take the rolling mean over all
these annual periods then what we get is
a temperature series that looks like
this
now this is looks like an incredible
linear trend to me so i am proposing
that we use a linear model with just a
intercept a and then a gradient b so in
summary over these 160 years we can see
that the um
the long term trend in that average has
gone from 17 degrees celsius through to
19. now for the seasonal variation what
we're going to do is we're actually
going to de-trend that time series so
remove that moving average over time
and then i'm going to plot the
temperature series so this denoised
temperature time series reveals that
temperatures have somewhat uniform peaks
and troughs and what you can see there
is that potentially we can actually use
a fourier series to model this so here's
what a fourier series looks like we've
got
a zero which is our constant our
intercept and then we have the
summations over different orders of sine
and cos curves with different
coefficients so essentially here i've
got a model for seasonality which is
based on a complete general truncated
fourier series however many papers have
actually suggested that temperature
variation can actually be captured by
just the first order fourier series so
that is where i is equal to one
and we only have the first order here so
we just have simply a sine and then a
cos function
now
one paper actually used a simplified
representation of a single sign curve
and i am actually betting that this is
going to be able to hold all of the
information from our time series
potentially this is just going to be
overfitting with another two parameters
so we are going to compare the two of
them and see what the models look like
now with this second model with a
translation in that phase of theta what
we can actually do is separate this out
using one of the trigonometric
identities into sine and cos now what
you'll see is that we can actually
define
two coefficients a1 and b1
that's just going to be corresponding to
alpha sine theta and then alpha cos
theta we can then rewrite this
temperature seasonal component as a1 cos
omega t plus b1 sine omega t here alpha
is equal to the square root of the sum
of the squares of a1 and b1 coefficients
and then the theta is equal to uh arctan
uh a1 over b1 trended and seasonality
removed well essentially we have this
deterministic seasonal mean of the d
noise time series that can be modeled
like this so essentially we've got this
temperature of our trend in our seasonal
component and here are our two models
that we're going to compare the first
one is that general
first order fourier series and then the
second is just the sine curve now the
assumption that we're going to make here
is that
the speeds of the seasonal processes are
the same and that is omega
2 pi over 365 days in a year now i don't
want to actually leave that as a
parameter in the model because again i'm
worried about overfitting and then funny
kinks so we'll actually enforce that
detail
now model fit in by non-linear least
squares here we're actually going to be
using sci pi optimize curve fit which is
an implementation of the levenberg
marquard theorem so lma theorem and
essentially this is just a non-linear
least squares problem
in solution that combines both the
gaussian newton
algorithm so gma with gradient descent
now we won't get into the details but
all we're doing is we're trying to
minimize the sum of the square
deviations and then some of the square
deviations
are actually calculated by using those
two algorithms before so when i first
look at the two models overlapped with
each other
they were essentially the same but
obviously the model fit general in the
black has
two more parameters than the uh just the
model fit with a sine code so therefore
from a principle of parsonomy i was
definitely going to pick just the sine
curve because i could represent all my
deviations in my model completely with
just the sine function
however
there is a second thing that i noticed
that was wrong with these two images if
you see the first image is from the
first period from
1859 in the initial years and then the
last period is from the last couple of
years and what you'll notice is that
there's actually seems to be a bit of a
phase shift so
the peaks are still occurring in the
data and the temperature data and the
troughs at the exact same time
however what's happened is that my model
has actually fitted
we've got a leading phase difference
with our top graph so in the earlier
years and then a lag in phase difference
in our models in the most recent years
so i sat here and stumbled over this
question for a while before really
realizing that it was our assumption
on our speed of the seasonal processes
so our frequency that was incorrect
here i assumed that this omega the
frequency was 2 pi over 365 but because
we're using such a large
number of data points approximately 160
years the phase shift occurs because of
leap years adding up to approximately 40
days
so this .25 so because a year is 365.2
or thereabouts
days per year this was leading to a
40-day phase change
and essentially when we remade the
assumption of omega 2 pi over
365.25
we got a great fit for our trend and
seasonality
so our actual model that we end up with
is
our simplified model so by parsonaby we
chose the sine curve and then the trend
component with our a and b terms
so with all our fitted coefficients in
there
we have 16.8 for a our intercept we've
got a really small coefficient 6.32
times 10 to the power of negative 5 for
our gradient in temperature over time
and time is ordinal numbers starting at
0 from the year 1859
now for alpha we've got 5.05 and then
our omega our defined frequency and
theta parameterized and our estimate
ended up as 1.27
so now that we've removed this
deterministic seasonality
from our time series what's left what
are the residuals look like and
essentially this detended and removed
seasonality form now here in our plots
on the left hand side i've got residuals
but then obviously i've made the time
series in the second plot at the bottom
a lot smaller so you can see more
granular changes and on the right hand
side i've shown the auto correlation and
the partial auto correlation and what i
want you to note is the partial auto
correlation function
really has quite a high core
coefficient in the first lag term
so this is the first issue essentially
we can see that there's strong partial
correlation identified at one lag and
this is indicating that maybe we might
need some kind of autoregressive model
to actually account
for this change in temperature now as
we'll find out later this is no
coincidence and we'll explain why in our
next video when we go into the
stochastic modelling of daily average
temperature
now the second issue occurred when i
looked at the probability plot model so
i looked at the qq plot
where we're comparing this error
distribution to the normal distribution
on the left hand side i have ordered
values of my temperature deviations and
on the
x-axis i have the normal distributions
and what you can see is a huge deviation
after two standard deviations so in
terms of z scores after two standard
deviations uh the probability of getting
that within my data set was about 3.6
versus the normal distribution of 2.3
and we can see a large amount of skew in
the histogram plot
so 0.63 and we can observe that kurtosis
so the fact tails 4.2 in comparison to 3
for the normal distribution
so the second error was that the area
distribution is not normally distributed
and we've just determined that visually
but there are models that you could
check with but this is because of the
presence of extreme temperature
deviation this is another issue that we
have to handle of our model and get to
the bottom of why this is occurring and
i have a sneaky suspicion it's to do
with temperature volatility and
seasonality so here are the academic
papers that i took a look at to actually
compile some of these this information
and this series in general so thank you
very much for listening and i'll see you
in the next one where we go and explore
some of the issues that we've just faced
[Music]
you